<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The wars in Germany vvith the taking of the seuerall townes by the Marquesse Spynola, and the present estate of the whole armie now on foote, in right of the emperour, sent from the Pope. Emperour. King of Spaine. Archduke. The cardinals. And Germaine prelasts. Together with the present estate of the contrary armie, conducted by Graue Maurice of Nassau, and the townes by him taken. Truely translated out of Dutch and French into English: and printed at Antvverpe the third of September. 1614.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11796</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118829</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854036</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854036</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19442</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19442)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The wars in Germany vvith the taking of the seuerall townes by the Marquesse Spynola, and the present estate of the whole armie now on foote, in right of the emperour, sent from the Pope. Emperour. King of Spaine. Archduke. The cardinals. And Germaine prelasts. Together with the present estate of the contrary armie, conducted by Graue Maurice of Nassau, and the townes by him taken. Truely translated out of Dutch and French into English: and printed at Antvverpe the third of September. 1614.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By E. Allde and T. Snodham] for Nathaniell Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC; Allde printed quires A-B, Snodham the rest.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Germany --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19442:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19442:1"/>
            <p>The Wars in Germany, With the taking of the ſeuerall townes by the Marqueſſe Spynola, and the preſent eſtate of the whole Armie now on foote, in right of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ſent from the <hi>Pope. Emperour. King of Spaine. Archduke.</hi> The <hi>Cardinals.</hi> And <hi>Germaine Prelats.</hi> Together with the preſent eſtate of the contrary Armie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> and the Townes by him taken. <hi>Truely tranſlated out of Dutch and French into Engliſh: and printed at</hi> Antwerpe <hi>the third of September.</hi> 1614.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of Ambrogio or Ambrosio Spinola, or a man in armour with a musket or gun and sword standing over a house in the countryside</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>Nathaniell Butter.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:19442:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19442:2"/>
            <head>A true relation of the taking of the towne of <hi>Aix</hi> or <hi>Accon, Weeſell</hi> and diuers other townes in Germanie by the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> generall of the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Armie; vnder pretence to reduce them to the obedience of the Emperour, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion they call Catholique. Together, with a full declaration of the whole armie now on foote ready to ioyne with the aforeſaid Marqueſſe, being ſent from the Pope, Emperour, Archduke, Conclaue of Cardinalls, and the Catholique Prelats of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie,</hi> and intituled the moſt Chriſtian league: Their numbers, enſignes, and Emblemes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O enter into the boſomes of Princes, or from a prophetique bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to interpret the hidden myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, ſhows in an ignorant preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nature, ſuch an impudence as can neither finde warrantie nor excuſe: therefore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19442:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> to trace myne Authors relation truly without any inquitie of the grounds, ends or determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of theſe ſtrange, ſodaine, and vnlookt-for garboyles, which haue euen with much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, ſet open all the eyes and eares in <hi>Eu-</hi> You ſhall vnderſtand that about the fiue <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And twentyth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, in this preſent yere 1614. according to the <hi>Roman</hi> computation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spinola</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming before <hi>Accon.</hi>
               </note> and the fifteenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in our account: The Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> (to whom they giue the title of excellence) being generall of the king of <hi>Spaines</hi> forces, came with a power of 1500. horſe, and 12000. foote, before a Towne in <hi>Cleueland</hi> called <hi>Aix</hi> or <hi>Accon,</hi> famous both for the antiquitie thereof: as alſo for certaine hot Bathes which are therein, but eſpecially for the priuiledge of keeping (as <hi>Guychardine</hi> reports) of an Iron crowne wherewith the Emperours are crowned at their firſt elections. Before this towne the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> with his forces ſet downe and planted againſt it three peeces of Cannon vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Saint <hi>Silueſters</hi> Hill, &amp; foure other great field peeces of Braſſe at the gate of the bridge againſt the great Tower or Bulwarke: yet before he began to make any ſhot or play v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the towne, he ſent certaine Ambaſſadors into the town, vpon whoſe deliberate &amp; perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue intreaties,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Accon</hi> taken by compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> the townſ-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accorded to make compoſition, vpon theſe conditions following.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19442:3"/> Firſt, that all Soldiers of what name title or qualitie ſoeuer, being then reſident in the town (being at that inſtant to the number of ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred) ſhould depart from thence, with bag and baggage, full arm'd, Drums beating, and their enſignes diſplayd, which were of white ſilke chargd with a blacke croſſe. Alſo that they ſhould haue ſafe conduct for fortie Carts to conuay and carie them &amp; their baggage: to all which the Marqueſſe accorded. Now as Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Iohn Van Diick alias Seram</hi> and <hi>Mounſieur de Potlites,</hi> with Captain <hi>Peter Galon de Meres</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenborch</hi> ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, were iſſuing out of the towne with their white enſignes flying and chargd as beforeſaid with blacke croſſes, diuers wealthy Burgers or men of account in the towne, whether fearfull of euills to come, or ſuſpitious of euills with which they had beene formerly acquainted, or ſtirred vp by their conſcience then likely to taſt tyranny, attempted to iſſue out of the towne, with the ſouldiours, but were by ſtrong hand hindred and turnd backe againe, by certaine bands or companies of <hi>Almaines</hi> to the number of 600. who entred at the ſame gate at which they departed.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19442:4"/>
            <p>Alſo at the ſame inſtant at another gate of the towne called <hi>Collogne</hi> port or gate, entred ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther company of <hi>Almaines</hi> equall to the former number.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe at the Bridge port or gate, there entred other ſixe enſignes of <hi>Almaines,</hi> who preſently marched vp into the towne, eſpecially to the place where the Proteſtants were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to heare their preaching.</p>
            <p>An other part of the army marched towards a place in the Towne called the <hi>Aſſes</hi> head, where other Proteſtants did exerciſe their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; The reſt of the Army went to the Cytadell or Towne Hall neare to the Hoſpitall, without hurting or offending any that were of that which they cal the Catholique Religion, whom likewiſe they exempted and made free from all charge, disburſments or taxations due for the reliefe of their Souldiours, lodging the army only vpon the charge of the Proteſtants, whom they ſuggeſted to haue (whilſt they were maſters of the towne) ſtopped and barred againſt them all theſe gates or entrances; that is to ſay firſt the port <hi>Royall,</hi> ſecondly, the Hill port; thirdly, the <hi>Zongle</hi> port; fourthly, the port <hi>Albertus;</hi> fiftly, the port <hi>Winaerte Bongaerts;</hi> ſixtly the <hi>Rooſt</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19442:4"/> port, and laſtly, Saint <hi>Iames</hi> port; not leauing any open for vſe but theſe only: the Bridge port, the port of <hi>Collogne,</hi> the <hi>Bortſcher</hi> port, and the <hi>Younkers</hi> port.</p>
            <p>The twentie ſeauenth of Auguſt, the Army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe from before the towne, and marched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome two leagues from <hi>Aix</hi> or <hi>Accon,</hi> and there encamped againe.</p>
            <p>The eight and twentith day of Auguſt the Army aroſe,<note place="margin">The taking of the Towne of <hi>Duren</hi>
               </note> and marched before the Towne of <hi>Duren,</hi> againſt which they encamped them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againe, and whilſt the Army there lay, there came out of the ſaid towne of <hi>Duren</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine principall men of great account and rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning mounted on horſ-back, and apparelled all in blacke, who by a mutuall and generall conſent were ſent out of the towne, as agents or negotiators for all the reſt, humbly to craue that it would pleaſe his Emperyall Maieſtie to pardon their offences and miſdemeanors how euer ignorantly or otherwiſe committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: moſt humbly and affectionately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firing to render and ſubieſt themſelues to the Lawes and ordinances of his Emperiall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, bringing and offering the Keyes of the Towne to the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> which hee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19442:5"/> receiued in the name and right of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, with all the curteous humanitie that his great place could any way extend: All which accomplements being finiſhed, the very ſame day the Marqueſſe ſent into the towne two Companies or Enſigns of Souldiours being to the number of three hundred men well apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being vnder the command of the Count <hi>Emden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The taking of <hi>Merſweicke</hi> &amp; <hi>Rangleroy.</hi>
               </note>The ſame day alſo being the twentie eight of Auguſt the Army aroſe from this Towne of <hi>Duren,</hi> and marched forward toward <hi>Merſweicke</hi> and <hi>Rangleroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The taking of <hi>Nuys.</hi>
               </note>The nine and twentieth of the ſame moneth of Auguſt, the Armie marched towards the towne of <hi>Nuys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon the thirtieth day of Auguſt the chiefe Burgamaſter of <hi>Nuys</hi> came to ſalute the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>Spynola,</hi> being brauely attended, and his perſon drawen in a Caroach, with foure hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and after ſome conference and ordinarie accomplement, to which, none but themſelues were priuie, the Marqueſſe entred into the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19442:5"/> Towne with fiue troopes of horſe, whilſte all the reſt of the armie remained without the Towne.</p>
            <p>Aſſoone as the Marqueſſe had ordered and diſpoſed of the Towne of <hi>Nuys,</hi> and placed ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons as he liked beſt, without any ſtay at all, but euen the very ſelfe ſame day being the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of Auguſt, he departed thence, and marched towards <hi>Duſſeldorpe,</hi> which is about a league from <hi>Nuys,</hi> yet at his departure from <hi>Nuys</hi> the Towne diſcharged ſix Cannons in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Marqueſſe, and as it ſeemed in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie triumphant and gallant faſhion: after which the armie marched towards the towne of <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers-wert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thirtieth day of Auguſt aforeſaid,<note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Neuwenborch</hi> Ioynes with <hi>Spinola.</hi>
               </note> the Duke of <hi>Neuwenborch</hi> met and ioyned his armie with the Marqueſſe <hi>Spynola</hi> neare to the towne of <hi>Iuliet,</hi> which armie of the Dukes was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of ſeauen thouſand foote and one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand horſe, in ſo much that at that time the Marqueſſe <hi>Spynola's</hi> armie was increaſed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to be twentie ſixe thouſand foot, and foure thouſand and three hundred horſe, one thouſand Waggons for munition, euery wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19442:6"/> hauing three horſes, beſides Victualers &amp; other neceſſarie depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dants to the Army, which are in number aboue two thouſand waggons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A bridge made ouer the <hi>Rheyne.</hi>
               </note>The one and thirtieth day of Auguſt, being the day after the ioyning of theſe two great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies into one, they began to make a bridge ouer the <hi>Reine,</hi> a little aboue <hi>Rein-Berke</hi> betwixt the two forts; in the labour and workemanſhip of which Bridge was imploied aboue one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men, beſides Pyoners, and other mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall labourers.</p>
            <p>The Bridge being perfitted as it were in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie moment of time,<note place="margin">The taking of <hi>Orſoy.</hi>
               </note> the armie paſſed ouer and marched the firſt day of September to the towne of <hi>Orſoy,</hi> which they preſently tooke, and at the ſame inſtant there ariued at the ſame Towne of <hi>Orſoy,</hi> a companie with <hi>Italians</hi> which came out of the towne of <hi>Geldre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſacking of <hi>Mulham.</hi>
               </note>The ſame day they marched thence with the whole armie, and comming to the new built Cittie of <hi>Mulhem</hi> neare vnto <hi>Colloigne,</hi> beganne that day to ſacke, deſtroy, and make an vtter deuaſtation of the ſame, finding it as it ſeemed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19442:6"/> either vtterly vnpeopled, or ſo weakely proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of reſiſtance, that nothing ſtood to oppoſe their furies.</p>
            <p>The ſame day alſo the armie was drawne to <hi>Meures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Meurs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> being a towne lying againſt <hi>Rijnsburge,</hi> where the Gouernor or Commander thereof came forth, and with all humilitie and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſaluted the Marqueſſe <hi>Spynola,</hi> and ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained all ſuch conditions as were thought meete for the places ouer which he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</p>
            <p>The ſecond day of September the armie came and incamped before the town of <hi>Weeſell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The taking of <hi>Weeſell.</hi>
               </note> and hauing laine there the ſpace of two dayes, in the end tooke it by a moſt kind and friendly compoſition, and albeit be wholie inhabited by Proteſtants, and that <hi>Spynola</hi> hath put thereinto a Garriſſon of fiue hundred <hi>Spaniards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clemencie ſhewed to the Proteſtants.</note> yet in no degree whatſoeuer doth the Souldier offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt any of the Towneſmen; which clemency is ſuppoſed by the beſt iudgements, not to proceede ſo much from loue as from feare of after troubles, which might follow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny croſſe or tyrannicall proceeding in theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile and furious buſineſſes.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19442:7"/>
            <p>After the departure of this great armie from <hi>Weeſell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spynola <hi>before</hi> Reinsberch.</note> the Marqueſſe marched to <hi>Reinsberche,</hi> where he vrged many intreaties and offered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers capitulations, but all to no effect, for the towne being eſteemed impregnable, and as it were invincible, there was little hope left of the winning of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Graue Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> riſeth and marcheth to <hi>Emricke.</hi>
               </note>During the time that this great armie called the moſt Chriſtian league or warre, ranne thus like an vnreſiſtable flame through all the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels of <hi>Germanie,</hi> threatning an vtter loſſe to all the poore afflicted Proteſtants, as it is giuen out by moſt credible and aſſured information, from the one and the other ſide: The moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and for euer renowned Prince the <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> with a very great and ſtrong armie of all the beſt and moſt experienced ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> marched vp into the higher parts of thoſe Countries, and about the ſecond day of September in this preſent yeare 1614. (being the ſame time that the Marqueſſe <hi>Spynola</hi> tooke <hi>Weeſell</hi>) the aforeſaid moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent prince <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> beſieged and tooke a towne of the Catholiques called <hi>Emricke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Emrick</hi> taken.</note> vpon the ſelfe ſame conditions as the Marqueſſe had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19442:7"/> taken the town of <hi>Weeſell</hi> before, vſing the ſame clemencie and mercie (in a ſomewhat more larger meaſure) to the Catholiques, which hee vnderſtood had beene practiſed before by the Marqueſſe to the Proteſtants, as it ſeemeth, to giue the world notice, how farre hee prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a noble preſident before any iuſt wrath, ſeuerity or reuenge: a nature ſo rich and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in the boſome of ſo worthy a Prince, that it can neuer bee ſufficiently admired of any that take delight to hold their rancke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the beſt of the vertuous.</p>
            <p>The third day of this preſent moneth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,<note place="margin">Graue Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice <hi>and</hi> Graue Henricke <hi>march to</hi> Reys</note> the excellent Prince <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the moſt noble count <hi>Henricke,</hi> raiſed their armie from before <hi>Emricke,</hi> and marched to another towne neare adioyning thereunto called <hi>Reys</hi> in the Dukedome of <hi>Cleue,</hi> againſt which they layd a ſtrong ſiege and begirt the Towne round about, and there were remaining at ſuch time as theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other occurrents receiued their diſpatches; ſo that what ſucceſſe will iſſue from the ſame, may bee expected and wiſht, but no certaine truth can be related, onely the great all-ſeeing eye of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19442:8"/> the diuine iuſtice no doubt will order their counſails and actions, ſo as it may bee beſt for his owne glorie and his Churches comfort, againſt which, queſtionles was neuer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared ſo numberleſſe, ſtrong, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull an armie, as you may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the ſequell of the Diſcourſe which now followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19442:8"/>
            <head>A moſt true and full Relation of the ſeuerall parts and members of that moſt great and generall body of the moſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Catholike Army, knit and vnited toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> into one maine ſubſtance, by the Pope, the Emperour, the King of Spayne, the Arch-Duke of Auſtria, and all the Catholike Cardinals, Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, and other inferiour Prieſts of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie; with their ſeuerall Generals, and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of each particular Armies: their Names, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Diſpoſitions: together, with their ſeuerall Emblemes and Deuiſes, placed as Trophyes vpon each of their Standards, or Enſignes Royall: in ſuch ſort as they haue been moſt carefully taken by eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall eye-witneſſes and moſt truly publiſhed for the ſatisfaction of all Chriſtian people. A matter moſt famouſly remarkeable, and worthy of admiration of all that ſhall happen to reade, and with a charitable iudgement truely vnderſtand the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome few dayes (as it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out by moſt credible report) after the Duke of <hi>Niewenborch</hi> had ioyned his forces with the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> there came
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19442:9"/> alſo and ioyned with them theſe Armies fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Popes Armie.</note>Firſt, from the Popes Holineſſe (drawne as he vrgeth from a holy comiſeration of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cauſe) was ſent an Armie of two thouſand Horſemen, and fifteene thouſand footemen, with all neceſſary prouiſions needefull in ſuch a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but by the diſtreſſed Proteſtants it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectured; nay, almoſt now gathered to a full be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, that this his huge liberalitie and expence of Men and Treaſure would not haue come ſo freely, had not his deſigne ſome ayme at the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter extyrpation of them, and their vndoubted true Religion, which, ſhould it appeare or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in any greater manifeſtation, no doubt but all Chriſtian eares would be fild with his crueltie, and what he would guild with a noble charitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, would of the wiſeſt and moſt modeſt tongues be called a tyrannicall bloudineſſe, a foule and ignoble-title for a man of his holy Order, or a Prince of his great Place and Authoritie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note>This great Army of the Popes hath ouer is for Generall or chiefe Commander, one named
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19442:9"/> 
               <hi>Don Paſcor,</hi> or <hi>Paſtor,</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> a man of great birth, place, experience, and vallour, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Italians: He beareth in his Standard (which is all entirely redde without any other Embleme or Empreſa, the collour as it were,<note place="margin">His Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſa.</note> ſpeaking the anger and reuenge his aymes leuell at) and in the midſt thereof this Motto or words written, <hi>Mors &amp; Vita,</hi> Death and Life; ſome tranſlate it Death or Life; others dead or liuing, but I take it to be Death and Life; Death to his withſtanders; Life to ſuch as will be yoked to him. It hath beene reported by ſome, that he beareth in his redde Standard or Enſigne, a liuing man, ſtanding ouer a dead man, and a Latine ſentence written vnderneath, ſignifying, <hi>Thou haſt thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie:</hi> but this I rather take to belong to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Commaunder, being as it were with him a ſecond in authoritie.</p>
            <p>Next to this Army of the Popes, marcheth the Emperour <hi>Mathyas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note> his owne Army being two thouſand Horſemen, and twenty thouſand Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, compounded of ſeuerall Nations, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces; but all held well approued in Warre, and of a great expertation and experience.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19442:10"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note>The Generall, or chiefe Commaunder of this great Armie of the Emperours, is the great Lord of <hi>Rhodes;</hi> a man very highly eſteemed for valour, wiſedome, experience, and what elſe adorneth a perfect Souldiour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme.</note>Hee beareth in his Standard or Enſigne-Royall, which is all white, prefiguring a more hurtleſſe and innocent temper, mixt with much more clemency &amp; Iuſtice then the former, a Lady or Virgine aparayled in white alſo, and a Lyon ſtanding by her, with a word or Motto, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Both theſe belong to Accon:</hi> now there be ſome reporters which affirme that his Enſigne is all white, without any charge but onely cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine words, which ſignifie in Engliſh, <hi>I haue much to looke for, and neuer to runne away;</hi> others tranſlate it, <hi>I expect much, but howſoeuer I will not flye:</hi> but this as I ſayd of the former, may belong to ſome other high Commaunder; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer neyther but ſhow the ſtrength of a great and vndaunted reſolution.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19442:10"/>
            <p>Touching the King of <hi>Spaynes</hi> Forces, which is called the Armie of the moſt Catholique King,<note place="margin">The King of Spaynes Armie.</note> they are numbred for certaine to be fifteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Horſemen, and twelue thouſand Foote-men, being for the moſt part all naturall Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, well experienced and approued Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as drawne from his moſt worthieſt Gariſons, and other places, of his moſt Warlike imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>The Generall of this great and famous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, is the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> held amongſt all the Spaniards a man of rare valure, wiſedome, and all greatneſſe of minde, and one on whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation doth lodge the badge of much good fortune in all his former affaires, whether they haue beene by Land or Sea, which haue knit ſo vnto him the King his Maſters loue, that his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings haue beene accounted more ſwift then any other of his ranke: a good note of worthineſſe, if his vertues and lovaltie endeauour to keepe and preſerue them without tyranie or ambition.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19442:11"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme.</note>His Standard or Enſigne royall is all white like the Emperours, wherein is portrayed a man ſtanding with a chayne about his necke, yet as it ſeemeth either vnmanacled and at liberty, or at moſt but in a willing and moſt pleaſing ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, for vnderneath him is writ a ſentence, which ſignifieth in Engliſh, <hi>My Chayne ſhall binde others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now there be ſome Reporters that affirme, that in his Enſigne beſides the chayned man, there is a <hi>Tyger</hi> and a <hi>Beare,</hi> and the word as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-ſaid, and I will not ſtand much to argue the contrary; for although it make the body of the <hi>Embleme,</hi> like a ſurcharged coate, ſomewhat too much burdened, againſt the ſtrickt rules of our curious deuiſe-makers, yet are they all ſo ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, and ſo well expreſſing the reſolution of a ſtrong Conquerour, that they may well become the inuention of him to vvhom they are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19442:11"/>
            <p>Next this Armie is ranked the Armie of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus,</hi> Archduke of <hi>Austria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dukes Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note> and brother to the Emperour <hi>Mathyas,</hi> and are fully accounted to be one thouſand fiue hundred Horſe-men, and tenne thouſand Foote-men, all good and approued Souldiers, by him bred, and diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, with great perfection in the Neather-lands, and other places, to which his occurrents haue drawne him.</p>
            <p>The Generall of this Army is the Archbiſhop of <hi>Albyod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> a very Noble deſcended Gentleman, full of great ſpirit and vviſedome, and one of high eſtimation with the Archduke, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by this great imployment, and many other graces and fauours done him in other ſeruices, all which hee ſeeketh to acknowledge in his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe and preparation, for any imployment ſhall be fixed vpon him.</p>
            <p>His Standard or Enſigne royall, is all blacke,<note place="margin">His Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs.</note> and in the midſt thereof a withered Tree, and a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19442:12"/> ſentence vnderneath it, ſignifying in Engliſh, <hi>Waxe greene againe,</hi> or <hi>I will waxe greene againe.</hi> Some report that hee hath in his Standard a <hi>Hearce</hi> or <hi>Tomba,</hi> which in Herraldry is an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of diſpaire; but I referre that to ſome better intelligence, for I take the other to be much more proper, and better ſuiting with the goodneſſe of a Noble nature, which indeede is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten darkned with theſe horrid and dreadfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaging menaces.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates Armie.</note>Laſt of all, is an Armie leauied by all thoſe which they entitle Catholicke Prelates, in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> as Cardinals, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inferiour Prieſts, all which haue with a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall conſent drawne their mindes and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together, and from thence raiſed vp a power of one and twenty hundred Horſe men, and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene thouſand Foote-men, not ſo well experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced or approued in the Warres (by ſuppoſition) as the others be: but no doubt men daring e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and apt to goe on without either care or queſtion of the enterpriſe to vvhich they are drawne, as is commonly ſeene and allowed in men of their mercinarie quality: and doubtleſſe this Armie is compoſed of all Nations whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, their Purſes for the moſt part being the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19442:12"/> entire commanders of their ſtrengths, being by no other bond engaged to the obedience of their Lords and Maſters; ſo that who ſo euer is out of imployment in this Armie, may finde bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe to preoccupate his whole ſpirits withall.</p>
            <p>The Generall of this Armie thus gathered from the very fluxe and multiplicity of Maſters,<note place="margin">The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> is the Archbiſhop of <hi>Riffin,</hi> or as ſome call it S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Raffin,</hi> a man of great truſt and eſtimation, with all the Clergie in thoſe Countries, and much renowned for his valour, wiſedome, poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and many other ſouldierly qualities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath beene plentifully endewed, onely ſo violent in the blindneſſe of his Religion, or as they call it Catholick profeſſion, that many of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may without offence vndergoe the cenſure or badge of much blood and cruelty.</p>
            <p>His Enſigne or Guidon (for indeede it can haue no other title of greatnes added vnto it)<note place="margin">His Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs.</note> is all of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19442:13"/> a gray colour, portraying the grauity, ſoberneſſe, and diſcreation vvhich ſhould be imployed in thoſe mighty Deſſeynes, and moſt eſpecially from men of ſuch ſanctity and pureneſſe of life, as in right the Maſters of this Armie ſhould be, and in the middeſt of this gray Enſigne there is grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his full glory a full blowne and faire flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Lilly, with his naturall leaues, branches, and beauties about it, and vnderneath a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſignifying in Engliſh theſe words, <hi>Natures Innocence is the beſt cloathing:</hi> a Motto which no doubt promiſeth vertuouſly, if the iſſues be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the oſtentation: but if they be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for any contrary purpoſe to goodneſſe, as to expell from that long enriched Empire, the true preaching of the Goſpell, and profeſſion of the moſt true, auncient, Catholicke, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke Faith, there is no doubt but the ruines of their owne <hi>Babell</hi> will fall vpon them, and confound them; if otherwiſe it be for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Chriſtian Faith, and the abolliſhing of <hi>Mahomet</hi> and his blaſphemies, no doubt but their Armies will ſtand like the Iſraelites, and finde GOD himſelfe continually fighting their battailes: how euer, to that power be all their powers and actions referred who is the GOD and Maſter of the hearts of Emperours, Kings, and Princes.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19442:13"/>
            <p>The vniuerſall power and whole groſſe body of this entire Armie, conſiſteth of nine thouſand one hundred Horſemen, and ſeauenty two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Foote-men: the two bodies ioyned together make full foure-ſcore and one thouſand and one hundred able fighting men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Relation was Printed in</hi> Antwerpe, <hi>both in Dutch and French, as may appeare by the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19442:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19442:14"/>
            <head>An Aduertiſement to the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle READER, I haue giuen thee here the firſt and fulleſt taſtes of theſe high and ſtrange preparations in <hi>Germany,</hi> with that true plaineneſſe and want of flatterie, as I did receiue them imprinted by eſpeciall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in <hi>Antwerpe;</hi> and as more ſhall come to my hands ſo I will preſent them vnto thee
<pb facs="tcp:19442:15"/> with all integritie and ſoundnes of truth: holding it an vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſinne to adde to the Names or Actions of ſuch Mightie and Sacred Perſons, the leaſt falſehood or ſcandall that may any way bee imagined.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19442:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
